in this video
we're going to talk about two ways in
which we could calculate the root mean
square molecular speed of nitrogen gas
at 300 kelvin
so let's start with this formula it's
equal to 3
kt divided by the mass
now k
is boltzmann's constant and m is the
mass of a single nitrogen gas molecule
in kilograms
now using the periodic table the atomic
mass of nitrogen is 14.01
but in this problem we have two of them
so it's 28.02
atomic mass units
now we need to convert atomic mass units
to kilograms and the conversion is
pretty simple
and so here's what you need to do
you need to know that one atomic mass
unit
is
1.66
times 10 to the negative 27 kilograms
so let's multiply those two numbers
so you should get 4.651
times 10
to the negative 26 kilograms
so what we're going to do is take this
value plug it into this equation
boltzmann's constant is 1.38
times 10
to the negative 23
and the temperature is 300 kelvin
and now let's plug in the mass that we
have
so go ahead and type this in to your
calculator
so this will give you about 517
meters per second
and so that's the answer
now in chemistry
you might see this equation used more
often
3rt divided by capital m
which is the molar mass of n2
in kilograms per mole
now the atomic mass
we said was 14.01 times two
so that gave us the molar mass of 28.02
atomic mass units which is the same as
grams per mole
but we need to convert grams to
kilograms
and you need to know that one kilogram
is equal to a thousand grams
and so
28.02 divided by a thousand that's going
to be .02802
kilograms per mole
so this is the value that we're going to
plug in
to this formula
so the root mean square velocity is
going to be the square root of 3
and r is going to be 8.3145
and the temperature
is still 300 kelvin
divided by
the molar mass of 0.02802
so this will give you the same answer
of 517
meters per second
you